Guide to the National Council of American Soviet Friendship Records TAM.134
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series I: Administration, 1919-1990
  - Subseries I:C:: Minutes (1943-1990)
    - Membership Meeting, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 66)
    - Membership Meeting, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 67)
    - Membership Meeting, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 68)
    - Membership Meeting, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 69)
    - Membership Meeting, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 70)
    - Membership Meeting, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 71)
    - Membership Meeting, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 72)
    - Membership Meeting, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 73)
    - Membership Meeting, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 74)
    - Membership Meeting, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 75)
    - Midwest Regional Meeting, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 76)
    - Western Regional Conference, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Subseries I:D: Internal Documents, Public Statements (1947-1989)
    - Report on Activities, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 78)
    - Statment to San Francisco Conference, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 79)
    - Anti-Soviet Radio Broadcast, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 80)
    - Statement by Clergy Opposing US Foreign Policy in Greece and Turkey, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 81)
    - Statement on Foreign Policy, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 82)
    - Statement--A Message to the President, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 83)
    - Appeal to Congress Re: German Question, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 84)
    - Morford Statement on Vinson Mission, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 85)
    - Statement on Stalin Proposals, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 86)
    - Statement on Remarks of Secretary of State Dean Acheson, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 87)
    - Report--"Seven Years of the NCASF," by Jessica Smith, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 88)
    - An Open Letter to the American People -- Re: Bonn Agreement, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 89)
    - Report on Fieldtrip--Elizabeth Moos, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 90)
    - Statement: Eleventh Anniversary of Stalingrad Victory, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 91)
    - Outline, Notes--Hungarian Crisis, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 92)
    - Report--"Role and Program of the NCASF", 1958 (Box 1, Folder 93)
    - Reports to NCASF Members, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 94)
    - Soviet Anti-Semitism, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 95)
    - Outline Discussion of NCASF Program, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 96)
    - Report on Activities, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 97)
    - Statement on Vietnam War, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 98)
    - NCASF Prospectus, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 99)
    - Council Report, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 100)
    - Discussions, Statements--Czechoslovakia, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Statement on 25th Anniversary, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Program of NCASF, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Statement--Call to End the War and Racism, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Report of the Commission on Disarmament, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Religion in the USSR, 1971-1984 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Report on Structure and By-Laws, 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Statement--The Peaceful Settlement of US/USSR Differences, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Chicago Convention, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Resolution--MX Missile, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Proposals and Resolutions--General, 1981-1983 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Statements--General, 1981-1984 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Reports--Executive Director, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Chronology--American-Soviet Relations, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Subseries I:E: Correspondence (1919-1990)
    - Chairmen Correspondence
      - Corliss Lamont, 1943-1984 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      - William Howard Melish, 1947-1958 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      - John Kingsbury--Personal Correspondence, 1919-1945 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - John Kingsbury, 1920-1937 (Box 2, Folder 18)
      - John Kingsbury, 1938-1955 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - John Kingsbury/A.L. Pollock, 1931-1933 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - John Kingsbury/Florence Powers, 1928-1934 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - John Kingsbury--Asian and Pacific Peace Conference, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - Rockwell Kent, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - Rockwell Kent--Press Releases, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - Rockwell Kent, 1958-1969 (Box 2, Folder 25)
      - Rockwell Kent/Jessica Smith, 1954-1959 (Box 2, Folder 26)
      - Rockwell Kent/Jessica Smith, 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 27)
      - Rockwell Kent/Jessica Smith, 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 28)
      - Rockwell Kent/Jessica Smith, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 29)
      - Rockwell Kent/Jessica Smith, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 30)
      - Rockwell Kent/Jessica Smith, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 31)
      - John Cherveny, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Secretary
      - Henry Pratt Fairchild, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Executive Directors
      - Edwin S. Smith, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 34)
      - Memos to Local Leadership, 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 35)
      - Correspondence and Memos to NCASF Members, 1946-1974 (Box 2, Folder 36)
      - Mary Van Kleek, 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 37)
      - Paul Robeson, 1949-1958 (Box 2, Folder 38)
      - Members, 1954-1957 (Box 2, Folder 39)
      - Board Members, 1954-1958 (Box 2, Folder 40)
      - Jessica Smith, 1954-1958 (Box 2, Folder 41)
      - Otto Nathan, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 42)
      - Max Weber, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 43)
      - Anna Louise Strong, 1955-1957 (Box 2, Folder 44)
      - Harry F. Ward, 1955-1957 (Box 2, Folder 45)
      - Bert Jahr, 1955-1958 (Box 2, Folder 46)
      - John Kingsbury, 1955-1958 (Box 2, Folder 47)
      - Bishop Moulton, 1955-1958 (Box 2, Folder 48)
      - Elsie Tyndale, 1955-1958 (Box 2, Folder 49)
      - Albert Kahn, 1955-1959 (Box 2, Folder 50)
      - Scott Nearing, 1955-1959 (Box 2, Folder 51)
      - Executive Committee/NY Division, 1955-1960 (Box 2, Folder 52)
      - William Spofford, 1955-1960 (Box 2, Folder 53)
      - Rockwell Kent, 1955-1965 (Box 2, Folder 54)
      - Shirley DuBois, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 55)
      - Henry Pratt Fairchild, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - Howard Fast, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Alexander Trachtenberg, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Governor Elmer Benson, 1956-1957 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - A.J. Muste, 1956-1957 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - Alphaeus Hunton, 1956-1958 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - Tamara Mamedov, 1956-1958 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - Mary Dreier, 1956-1959 (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - Jerome Davis, 1957-1958 (Box 3, Folder 9)
      - Regional Memos, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      - John Baker, 1975-1977 (Box 3, Folder 11)
      - Gennady Fedosov, USSR/USA Society, 1975-1980 (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Memos to Societies, 1976-1984 (Box 3, Folder 13)
      - Morford Memorial, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 14)
      - Correspondence A-D, 1955-1970 (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - Correspondence E-H, 1955-1960 (Box 3, Folder 16)
      - Correspondence I-L, 1950-1976 (Box 3, Folder 17)
      - Correspondence M-P, 1954-1960 (Box 3, Folder 18)
      - Correspondence Q-T, 1950-1960 (Box 3, Folder 19)
      - Correspondence U-Z, 1955-1960 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Alan Thomson Correspondence
      - Memos to Executive Committee, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 21)
      - Memos to Executive Committee, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 22)
      - Memos to Executive Committee, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 23)
      - Memos to Executive Committee, 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 24)
      - Memos to Executive Committee, 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 25)
      - Memos to Societies, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 26)
      - Memos to Societies, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 27)
      - Memos to Societies, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 28)
      - Memos to Societies, 1986-1988 (Box 3, Folder 29)
      - Memos to Societies, 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 30)
      - Fact Sheets, 1981-1984 (Box 3, Folder 31)
      - Fact Sheets, 1985-1990 (Box 3, Folder 32)
      - General Correspondence, 1981-1990 (Box 3, Folder 33)
      - "Partisans of Vilna", Aviva Kempner, 1983-1986 (Box 3, Folder 34)
      - USSR, 1985-1989 (Box 3, Folder 35)
      - William Mandel, 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 36)
      - Philip Zwerling, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - General Correspondence
      - Henry L. Stimson, 1944-1945 (Box 3, Folder 38)
      - Claude Pepper, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 39)
      - Reconciliation Trips, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 40)
      - Edward R. Stettinius, Jr., 1945 (Box 3, Folder 41)
      - Cultural and Scientific Conference for World Peace, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 42)
      - Progressive Party, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 43)
      - World Congress of Defenders of Peace--Paris, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 44)
      - "Washington and You", 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 45)
      - Society for German-Soviet Friendship, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 46)
      - American-Russian Institute, 1950-1980 (Box 3, Folder 47)
      - California Labor School (Holland Roberts), 1951-1956 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Committee on the Maintenance of American Freedom, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - New World Review, 1953-1976 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Council on African Affairs (Alphaeus Hunton), 1954-1955 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - The Nation, 1954-1957 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - World Fellowship, Inc. (Willard Uphaus, Charles Weller), 1954-1958 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - American Labor Party, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - American Peace Crusade, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - Emma Lazarus Federation of Jewish Women, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - Freedom Associates, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      - People's Institute (Claude Williams), 1955-1956 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      - Religious Freedom Committee, 1955-1956 (Box 4, Folder 12)
      - General Correspondence, 1955-1957 (Box 4, Folder 12.1)
      - American Friends Service Committee, 1955-1958 (Box 4, Folder 13)
      - Ted Bayer, 1955-1958 (Box 4, Folder 14)
      - Board of World Peace, 1955-1958 (Box 4, Folder 15)
      - Emergency Civil Liberties Committee, 1955-1958 (Box 4, Folder 16)
      - Elizabeth Moos, 1955-1958 (Box 4, Folder 17)
      - Committee for the Protection of the Foreign Born, 1955-1959 (Box 4, Folder 18)
      - Muriel Symington, 1955-1959 (Box 4, Folder 19)
      - Friends Committee on National Legislation, 1956-1957 (Box 4, Folder 20)
      - USSR Society for Cultural Relations with Foreign Countries (Voks), 1956-1958 (Box 4, Folder 21)
      - Dwight Eisenhower, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 22)
      - Soviet Peace Committee, 1960-1970 (Box 4, Folder 23)
      - NCASF Staff, 1961-1967 (Box 4, Folder 24)
      - Institute of Soviet-American Relations, 1966-1969 (Box 4, Folder 25)
      - Ukranian Friendship Society, 1968-1975 (Box 4, Folder 26)
      - Embassy of the USSR, 1973-1978 (Box 4, Folder 27)
      - Council on International Educational Exchange, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 28)
      - Itineraries: Colleges and Universities, 1974-1978 (Box 4, Folder 29)
      - Committee of Youth Organizations, 1974-1979 (Box 4, Folder 30)
      - NCASF Exchange Programs: Information Requests, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 31)
      - Society Requests for Films, 1980-1982 (Box 4, Folder 32)
      - NCASF/Societies, 1981-1989 (Box 4, Folder 33)
      - Sister Cities International, 1982-1986 (Box 4, Folder 34)
      - NCASF--USSR/USA Societies, 1983-1988 (Box 4, Folder 35)
      - Requests for NCASF Information, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 36)
      - USA-USSR Church Rleations Committee, 1984-1985 (Box 4, Folder 37)
      - Downstate Nuclear Weapons Freeze Campaign, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 38)
      - Unsanswered Requests, 1985-1988 (Box 4, Folder 39)
      - Requests for Penpals, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 40)
      - Proctor Jones, 1987-1989 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Subseries I:F: Legal (1945-1989)
    - Charters and Contracts
      - NCASF Certificate of Incorporation, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 42)
      - Agreements of Cooperation with USSR Society, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 42.1.)
    - Defense of NCASF
      - Correspondence, 1945-1962 (Box 4, Folder 43)
      - Citizens United to Abolish the Wood-Rankin Committee, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 44)
      - Richard Morford Case, 1946-1950 (Box 4, Folder 45)
      - Corliss Lamont Case, 1946-1954 (Box 4, Folder 46)
      - NCASF Public Statements, 1946-1955 (Box 4, Folder 47)
      - General Memos, 1946-1952 (Box 4, Folder 48)
      - NCASF Indictments, Petition, Notes, 1947-1951 (Box 4, Folder 49)
      - Reports, 1947-1956 (Box 4, Folder 50)
      - Mundt Bill, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 51)
      - Correspondence--Dean of Canterbury Visit, 1948-1954 (Box 4, Folder 52)
      - NCASF Suit Against Attorney General, 1948-1954 (Box 4, Folder 53)
      - SACB v. NCASF--Motions, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 54)
      - Loyalty Review Board, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 55)
      - Appeal to Dismiss Smith Act, 1949-1956 (Box 4, Folder 56)
      - Government Statements, Opinions of Justices, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 57)
      - John Kingsbury Case, 1951-1955 (Box 4, Folder 58)
      - Correspondence--David Rein (Lawyer), 1951-1960 (Box 4, Folder 59)
      - SACB Petition, Proposed Findings, Recommendation, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 60)
      - SACB v. NCASF, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 61)
      - Deposition of Dean of Canterbury, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 62)
      - "I Spied on the Reds for the FBI" Article on NCASF, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 63)
      - Statements, Comment by NCASF Lawyer, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 64)
      - Campaign to Repeal McCarran Act, 1954-1955 (Box 4, Folder 65)
      - Bachrach Case/Smith Act, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 66)
      - NCASF v. SACB--Legal Brief, Report, 1956-1963 (Box 4, Folder 67)
      - Alan Thomson Defense Fund, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - Subseries I:G: Members and Sponsors, Finances (1943-1988)
    - Sponsors of NCASF--Letters of Acceptance, 1943-1944 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Sponsors and Members--Resignations, 1946-1955 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Contributions from Societies, 1982-1987 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Finances, 1985-1988 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Fundraising, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Subseries I:H: Committees and Local Councils (1943-1988)
    - Committees
      - Architects Committee, 1944-1947 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - Committee on the Arts, 1943-1946 (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - Building Industry Committee, 1945-1947 (Box 5, Folder 8)
      - Committee to Seek NCASF Chairman, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 8.1)
      - Cultural Committee, 1943-1970 (Box 5, Folder 9)
      - Committee on Education, 1944-1964 (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - Exhibit Department, 1944-1945 (Box 5, Folder 11)
      - Nationalities Committee--Material for Pamphlet, 1943-1969 (Box 5, Folder 12)
      - Publicity Department, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 13)
      - Committee on Racism, undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
      - Science Committee, undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
      - Speakers Bureau, 1945-1984 (Box 5, Folder 16)
      - Travel Committee, 1966-1976 (Box 5, Folder 17)
      - Committee of Women, 1943-1965 (Box 5, Folder 18)
      - Youth Committee, 1975-1985 (Box 5, Folder 19)
      - Youth Committee--Correspondence, 1972-1979 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Local Councils
      - General Information on Local Councils, 1943-1988 (Box 5, Folder 21)
      - Bay Area--Letter From Morford, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 22)
      - Berkeley Council, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 23)
      - Boston Council, 1976-1980 (Box 5, Folder 24)
      - Buffalo Council, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 25)
      - Southern California Council, 1943-1981 (Box 5, Folder 26)
      - Chicago Council, 1942-1980 (Box 5, Folder 27)
      - Cleveland Council, 1944-1981 (Box 5, Folder 28)
      - Conference of Local Councils, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 29)
      - Delaware Valley Council (Philadelphia), 1980 (Box 5, Folder 30)
      - Detroit Council, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 31)
      - Florida Council, 1979-1980 (Box 5, Folder 32)
      - Madison Council, 1980-1988 (Box 5, Folder 33)
      - Massachusetts Council, 1943-1953 (Box 5, Folder 34)
      - Milwaukee Council, 1977-1980 (Box 5, Folder 35)
      - Minneapolis Council, 1975-1980 (Box 5, Folder 36)
      - New York Association for American-Soviet Friendship--Peace Committee, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 37)
      - Metropolitan New York Council, 1976-1977 (Box 5, Folder 38)
      - New York City--Neighborhood Committees, 1945-1964 (Box 5, Folder 39)
      - Oklahoma City Council, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 40)
      - Pittsburgh Council, 1978-1980 (Box 5, Folder 41)
      - Portland Council, 1977-1979 (Box 5, Folder 42)
      - San Diego Council, 1972-1979 (Box 5, Folder 43)
      - Seattle Council, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 44)
      - Washington, DC Council, 1976-1979 (Box 5, Folder 45)
      - Washington Council, 1974-1980 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Subseries I:I: Publications and Educational Materials (1945-1985)
    - NCASF Brochure, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - Bibliographies--Childrens Books in the USSR 1946 (Box 5, Folder 47.1)
    - USSR Bibliographies, 1949-1985 (Box 5, Folder 48)
    - Recording--Script "The Bridge", 1955 (Box 5, Folder 49)
    - Requests for Information, 1955-1960 (Box 5, Folder 50)
    - Publications--Correspondence, 1955-1957 (Box 5, Folder 51)
    - "USSR in Questions and Answers"--E. Moos, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 52)
    - Educational Materials--Photograph Exhibits, 1957-1960 (Box 5, Folder 53)
    - Publications List, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 54)
    - "The Story of American-Soviet Relations" H. Ward, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 55)
    - "Total Disarmament in Four Years", 1959 (Box 5, Folder 56)
    - "Soviet Education Today and Tomorrow"-- E.Moos, 1959-1960 (Box 5, Folder 57)
    - Educational Materials--Loan Library, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 58)
    - Soviet Education Bibliography, 1961-1963 (Box 5, Folder 59)
    - Proposals for Exchange Bulletins on the Arts, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 60)
    - "Lenin's Humanity" H. Parsons, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 61)
    - Russian Language Classes, 1982-1988 (Box 5, Folder 62)
    - "Honoring Their Word" D. Rosenberg, 1983-1985 (Box 5, Folder 63)
    - Soviet Life, 1984-1986 (Box 5, Folder 64)
    - NCASF Film Catalog, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Friendship News, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Bibliography on the USSR, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Drawings by Soviet Children, undated (Box 6, Folder 3.1)
    - Exhibit "Mother and Child Care in the Soviet Union", undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - NCASF Library and Research Service, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Playscript "Caviar to the General", undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Publication "Is American-Soviet Coexistence Possible?", undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Publication "The Hell Bomb and You", undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Publication "Stalingrad!", undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Publications--Memo from Jessica Smith, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Series II: Activities, Programs, Special Projects, 1943-1990
  Series II: Activities, Programs, and Special Projects (1943-1990), is divided into four subseries.
  Subseries II.A: NCASF Activities, contains 147 folders, the largest subseries in the collection. The bulk of these activities took place in the 1940's and 1950's, and consist mainly of rallies, conferences, dinners, testimonials, fundraisers, exhibits, and receptions. The types of materials are reports, correspondence, minutes from planning meetings, and speeches. Included in this collection are materials from recurring NCASF events, such as the Annual American-Soviet Friendship Rallies at Madison Square Garden and Red Army Dinners. Early Council activities included tributes to Josef Stalin and Foreign Minister Vishinski. Beginning in the late 1940's and early 1950's, the scale of these events noticeably decreased, reflecting changes in the national political climate and the onset of the Cold War. During this period, the kind of activities gradually changed, from mass political rallies to smaller, cultural events. More recent Council activities include participation in the New York City Board of Education "City as School" program, a 1985 American-Soviet Childrens' Art Exchange, and a 1987 educational program on Chernobyl.
  Subseries II.B: Exchange and Travel Programs, contains material from travel programs and tours initiated by the NCASF. About three-quarters of this subseries consists principally of applications and lists of delegations to the Council's Camp Artek program. This subseries also contains itineraries, tour reports, program applications, and publicity arrangements from a number of other Council-sponsored USSR tours and delegations.
  Subseries II.C: Campaign for a People's Peace Treaty/People's Appeal for Peace (1982-1989) documents the administration and activities of this Council-sponsored organization, whose activities failed to culminate with the presentation of peace petitions to Ronald Reagan in 1987. Included in this subseries is information on the Campaign's "pairing project," an attempt to pair US and Soviet cities through correspondence and exchange programs.
  Subseries II.D: Other Organizations Concerned with American-Soviet Relations (1944-1989), is arranged alphabetically. This series principle contains publications and newsletters, as well as some correspondence, from organizations such as the National Council for Canadian-Soviet Friendship, the American-Soviet Youth Forum, and the Soviet American Sail.
  Content Warning: Some audiovisual recordings in this series contain explicit content describing violence against women.
  - Subseries II:A: NCASF Activities (1943-1989)
    - Second Congress of American-Soviet Friendship, 1943 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Red Army Dinner, 1943 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - "Open Letter to the American People" Project 1943 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - American Soviet War Exhibit, 1943 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Tenth Anniversary of US/USSR Diplomatic Relations, 1943 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - "Women for Victory" Meetings, 1944 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Red Army Dinner, 1944 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Conference on Education in the Soviet Union, 1944 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - American-Soviet Friendship Rally, 1944 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - American-Soviet Friendship Rally, 1944 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - "Salute to the GIs of the United Nations", 1944 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - American-Soviet Building Conference, 1945 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - American-Soviet Friendship Rally--Messages (Includes Albert Einstein Letter), 1945 (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - American-Soviet Friendship Rally--Requests for Messages, 1945 (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - American-Soviet Friendship Rally--Speeches, 1945 (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - American-Soviet Friendship Rally --Instructions to Speakers, 1945 (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - American-Soviet Friendship Rally--Meeting Outside New York, 1945 (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Dean of Canterbury Visit, 1945 (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - Cultural Conference, 1945 (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - Red Army Dinner, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - "Get Together with Russia" Rally--Correspondence, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 31)
    - "Get Together with Russia" Rally--Script, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 32)
    - "Get Together with Russia" Rally--Speeches, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 33)
    - "Get Together with Russia" Rally--Budget, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 34)
    - Childrens Book Week, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 35)
    - American-Soviet Friendship Dinner, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 36)
    - "US Policy in Germany and World Peace" --Meeting, 1948 (Box 6, Folder 37)
    - Conference on Public Affairs, 1948 (Box 6, Folder 38)
    - Spring Festival and Bazaar, 1948 (Box 6, Folder 39)
    - Rally for Peace, 1948 (Box 6, Folder 40)
    - "Roll Call for Peace"--Peace Campaign, 1948 (Box 6, Folder 41)
    - Childrens Book Week, 1948 (Box 6, Folder 42)
    - Dean of Canterbury Visit, 1948-1949 (Box 6, Folder 43)
    - Peace Rally--Madison Square Garden, 1948-1949 (Box 6, Folder 44)
    - Washington Conference on Foreign Affairs, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 45)
    - Melish Resignation Speech at Testimonial Dinner, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 46)
    - NCASF Annual Autumn Dinner, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - Research and Study Conference on American-Soviet Relations, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 48)
    - Vishinski Dinner, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 49)
    - Vishinski Dinner--Correspondence, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 50)
    - Congress on American-Soviet Relations: Eastern Seaboard Conference, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - "Outlaw the Atomic Bomb" Rally, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - Stalin's 70th Birthday Symposium, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 53)
    - Congress For Peace, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 54)